Guide to the Bernard Barber Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Bernard Barber Papers
1938-1988.
Barber, Bernard.
27 linear ft (ca. 29,000 items in 59 boxes)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY.
4078839
Bernard Barber (1918-2006) was a Professor of Sociology at Barnard College for over 35 years, from 1952 until his retirement. He wrote several books, many articles, and was a pioneer in the sociology of science and the theory of social structure.
History
Bernard Barber (1918-2006) was a Professor of Sociology at Barnard College for over 35 years, from 1952 until his retirement. He wrote several books, many articles, and was a pioneer in the sociology of science and the theory of social structure.
Scope and Content
Correspondence, conference papers and notes, lectures, Barnard College administrative records, book review manuscripts, financial records for his research grants, book manuscripts, and his college notes. Correspondence with sociologists and other professional colleagues concerning his writing, teaching, and Barnard College administrative affairs, and with his friends. Major correspondents include Daniel Bell, Robert K. Merton, David Riesman, George Sarton, and Talcott Williams. There are also letters from Harry Elmer Barnes, Richard Hofstadter, Edward Kennedy, Margaret Mead, Ashley Montagu, and C.P. Snow.
Series 4: 1979-1988. These materials were added to the papers in 1988. This series consists of five categories pertaining to the professional career of Bernard Barber. The correspondence series contains a general chronological file, as well as alphabetical sets by correspondents and by topics. It also contains correspondence regarding Barber's books, which include SCIENCE AND THE SOCIAL ORDER (1953) and SOCIAL STRATIFICATION (1957). The Professional Activities category contains a wide range of files on Barber's work outside Columbia University, including service on various federal and private committees, such as the Drug Research Board of the National Science Council and the Human Subjects Review Committee, as well as his membership in a multitude of professional organizations, including the American Sociological Association, whose Ethics Committee he chaired from 1960-1976. The Manuscripts file contains published articles and typed drafts of articles for various sociological journals as well as several book reviews. The Research file contains Barber's scholarly work, including an extensive study of the practice of informed consent. The Teaching section contains material from Barber's career as a faculty member at Barnard College, Columbia University.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in four series:
Series I. Cataloged Correspondence
Series II. Uncataloged Correspondence, 1941-1979
Series III. Uncataloged Manuscripts and Notes--A-Z
Series IV. 1979-1988
Subseries IV.1. Uncataloged Correspondence
Subseries IV.2. Professional Activities
Subseries IV.3. Manuscripts
Subseries IV.4. Research Files
Subseries IV.5. Teaching
Subjects
Barnard College--Faculty.; Bell, Daniel.; Merton, Robert King, 1910-2003.; Riesman, David, 1909-2002.; Sarton, George, 1884-1956.; Williams, Talcott, 1849-1928.; Barnes, Harry Elmer, 1889-1968.; Hofstadter, Richard, 1916-1970.; Kennedy, Edward Moore, 1932-; Mead, Margaret, 1901-1978.; Montagu, Ashley, 1905-1999.; Snow, C. P. (Charles Percy), 1905-1980.; Sociology--Study and teaching.; Sociologists.; College teachers.
Access Restrictions
The following boxes are located off-site: 2-59. You will need to request this material from the Rare Book and Manuscript Library at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
1983 M83 Barber, Bernard Gift, 1983;1988
Gift of Professor Barber, 1983; 1988.
Finding aid in repository; folder level control.
- Series I. Cataloged Correspondence
  - Barnes, Harry Elmer (Box 1)
  - Barzun, Jacques (Box 1)
  - Bell, Daniel (Box 1)
  - Brinton, Crane (Box 1)
  - Bundy, McGeorge (Box 1)
  - Bush, Vannevar (Box 1)
  - Carey, Hugh L. (Box 1)
  - Dirksen, Everett McKinley (Box 1)
  - Eiseley, Loren Corey (Box 1)
  - Flexner, James Thomas (Box 1)
  - Hofstadter, Richard (Box 1)
  - Javits, Jacob Koppel (Box 1)
  - Jessup, Philip Caryl (Box 1)
  - Kaempffert, Waldemar (Box 1)
  - Kennedy, Edward Moore (Box 1)
  - Kennedy, Robert Francis (Box 1)
  - Knopf, Alfred A. (Box 1)
  - Kristol, Irving (Box 1)
  - Krock, Arthur (Box 1)
  - Leuchtenberg, William E. (Box 1)
  - McWilliams, Carey (Box 1)
  - Matthiessen, Francis O. (Box 1)
  - Mead, Margaret (Box 1)
  - Mills, C. Wright (Box 1)
  - Mondale, Walter Frederick (Box 1)
  - Montagu, Ashley (Box 1)
  - Nagel, Ernest (Box 1)
  - Needham, Joseph (Box 1)
  - Nelson, Benjamin (Box 1)
  - Podhoretz, Norman (Box 1)
  - Pusey, Nathan M. (Box 1)
  - Reston, James Barrett (Box 1)
  - Rhine, Joseph Banks (Box 1)
  - Riesman, David (Box 1)
  - Rothschild, Edmund Leopold de (Box 1)
  - Sagarin, Edward (Box 1)
  - Sarton, George (Box 1)
  - Sarton, May (Box 1)
  - Snow, Charles Percy, Baron Snow (Box 1)
  - Scheinfeld, Amram (Box 1)
- Series II. Uncataloged Correspondence, 1941-1979
  - 1941-1954 July (Box 2, Folder 1 to 6)
  - 1954 August-1957 (Box 3, Folder 7 to 11)
  - 1958-1959 (Box 4, Folder 12 to 15)
  - 1960-1961 September (Box 5, Folder 17 to 19)
  - 1961-1963 January (Box 6, Folder 20 to 23)
  - 1964 January-1964 May (Box 7, Folder 24 to 27)
  - 1964 May-1965 September (Box 8, Folder 28 to 31)
  - 1965 September-1967 May (Box 9, Folder 32 to 35)
  - 1967 May-1968 July (Box 10, Folder 36 to 39)
  - 1968 July-1970 March (Box 11, Folder 40 to 43)
  - 1970 March-1971 November (Box 12, Folder 44 to 47)
  - 1971 September-1973 February (Box 13, Folder 48 to 51)
  - 1973 March-1974 May (Box 14, Folder 52 to 55)
  - 1974 June-1975 September (Box 15, Folder 56 to 59)
  - 1975 October-1977 January (Box 16, Folder 60 to 63)
  - 1977 (Box 17, Folder 64 to 66)
  - 1978 June-1979 May (Box 18, Folder 67 to 69)
- Series III. Uncataloged Manuscripts and Notes--A-Z
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science (AAAS) Meeting, Chicago, Ethics, 1970 (Box 19)
  - "American Education and the Scientific Scene," 1958 July 28 (Box 19)
    (Speech)
  - "American Sociology in its Cultural Context," (Box 19)
    (3 drafts)
  - American Sociological Society (Box 19)
  - Sociology of Science Sessions, B. Barber, Chairman, 1957 (Box 19)
  - Nominations and Elections, 1957 (Box 19)
  - "Anti-Intellectualism," Society for the Psychological Study of Social Issues (Box 19)
  - Benson, Lee--Wayne Center (Box 19)
  - "Brief Bibliography for the Sociology of Science" (Box 19)
  - Brookings Conference, 1973 September (Box 19)
  - Brookings Institute, Williamsburg, 1963 May (Box 19)
  - Bureau of Applied Social Research, 1954-1955 (Box 19)
  - Case Methods of Instruction in American Professional Training" (Box 19)
  - "Concrete Sociology: A Study of Cases" (Box 19)
  - Council for Research in the Social Sciences, (2 Folders) (Box 19)
  - Daedalus, Ethics Conference, 1967 (Box 20)
  - George H.G. Daniels Affair (Box 20)
  - Division of Labor in Science (Box 20)
  - Drugs and Society (Box 20)
  - Duodecim Theological Society (Box 20)
  - Eastern Sociological Society, Ethics of Social Research, 1980 March (Box 20)
  - Ethics Conference, New York Academy of Sciences, 1969 May (Box 20)
  - "Experimentation on Humans: Another Civil Rights Frontier?" (Box 20)
  - "Family Status, Local-Community Status, and Social Stratification," Pacific Journal of Sociology (Box 20)
  - Fellowship Applications, 1959-1960 (Box 20)
  - "Floppy Eared Rabbits" (Box 20)
  - Flow of Scientific Information (Box 20)
  - Ford Foundation, Sociology of Science Seminar, 1953 September (Box 20)
  - Fulbright, History of Science (Box 21)
  - Glazer, Nathan, Article (Commentary comment} (Box 21)
  - Greap, Roy O., Ford Committee (Box 21)
  - Harvard Overseers Visiting Committee, (2 Folders) (Box 21)
  - History and Theory Review Article (Box 21)
  - Hoffman-LaRoche Conference, 1971 September (Box 21)
  - Ideas for Papers, Monographs, Books (Box 21)
  - Informed Consent Study (Box 21)
  - International Relations Theory Meetings, 1957 (Box 22)
  - International Sociological Society (ISA) Paper, 1957 (Box 22)
  - ISA Trend Report, Sociology of Science (Box 22)
  - Kinsey Report, Article (Box 22)
  - L-Dopa Study (Box 22)
  - Mount Sinai Course (Box 22)
  - Myth of the Rising Middle Class, (2 Folders) (Box 22)
  - National Institute of Health (NIH), Conference on Planning and Responsibility in Society, 1969 October (Box 22)
  - National Science Foundation (NSF), (2 Folders) (Box 22)
  - "Natural Science, Social Science and Value" (Box 23)
    (Unpublished article)
  - Qak Ridge, 1963 Summer (Box 23)
  - Occupational Prestige Structure, Notes (Box 23)
  - "On the Relation between Culture and Social Structure" (Box 23)
  - Papworth Review, Medical Counterpoint (Box 23)
  - Parsons, Talcott, (3 Folders) (Box 23)
  - Pittsburgh--Ethical Problems, 1975 (Box 23)
  - Princeton Social Mobility Discussion, 1965 November (Box 23)
  - Professions, (3 Folders) (Box 23)
  - Ramapo College Lecture, "Experimenting with Humans" (Box 24)
  - Reader, George, Project with (Box 24)
  - "Recent Trends in the Sociology of Knowledge and Science in the United States" (Box 24)
  - "Research on Injuries in Biomedical Research," New England Journal of Medicine Editorial (Box 24)
  - "Research on Research on Human Subjects" (Box 24)
  - Revista de Trabajo, Essay on Social Mobility Trends, Correspondence (Box 24)
  - University of Rhode Island talk, 1963 November (Box 24)
  - University of Rochester, Honors Exams, 1963 (Box 24)
  - Roe, Anne, National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH) Evaluation (Box 24)
  - Rose Monograph Series (Box 24)
  - Russell Sage Foundation, (3 Folders) (Box 24)
  - Salk Institute (Box 24)
  - Salzburg Seminar, 1956 Summer (Box 24)
  - Smithsonian Conference on Experimentation (Box 24)
  - Social Evolution (Box 25)
  - Social Roles of the Historian (Box 25)
  - Social Stratification, (7 Folders) (Box 25)
  - "Social Work and Social Science" (Box 25)
  - "Sociology of Science," Encyclopedia of the Social Sciences article (Box 25)
  - Social Science Research Council, National Security Policy, Princeton, 1963 June (Box 25)
  - "Structure of Scientific Competition" (Box 25)
  - Technology and Culture, Program Committee, 1963 (Box 26)
  - Technology and Values, American Association for the Advancement of Science, Dallas, 1968 December (Box 26)
  - "Tension, Conflict and Accommodation: Between Science and Humanism" (Box 26)
  - "Towards a New Social Policy on Dangerous Drugs" (Box 26)
  - "Towards a New View of the Sociology of Knowledge" (Box 26)
  - UNESCO Trend Report (Box 26)
  - Unity of Science, 1951 May (Box 26)
  - Volunteers, (2 Folders) (Box 26)
  - War Memorials (Box 26)
- Series IV. 1979-1988
  - Subseries IV.1. Uncataloged Correspondence
    - Chronological
      - 1979-1981 (Box 27)
      - 1981-1984 (Box 28)
      - 1984-1986 (Box 29)
      - 1986-1988 (Box 30)
    - Alphabetical by Correspondent (Box 30)
    - Alphabetical by Topic (Box 31)
    - Re: Books (Alphabetical by Title)
      - A-S (Box 32)
      - S (Box 33)
    - Correspondence with Publisher (Wiley) (Box 34)
  - Personal Papers (Box 34)
  - Subseries IV.2. Professional Activities
    - A-C (Box 35)
    - Center for Policy Research-Center for Social Sciences (Box 36)
    - Conferences (Box 37)
    - Committees (Box 37)
    - Drug Research Board (Box 38-39)
    - Human Subject Research Group-Human Subjects Review Committee (Box 40)
    - I-O (Box 41)
    - S-T (Box 42)
    - Seminars and Trips (Box 43)
    - Professional Organizations
      - A-Am (Box 44)
      - American Sociological Association
        - General (Box 45)
        - Ethics Committee
          - 1960-1967 (Box 46)
          - 1967-1976 (Box 47)
      - C-S (Box 48)
      - Society for the Social Study of Science (SSSS) (Box 49)
  - Subseries IV.3. Manuscripts
    - A-Pe (Box 50)
    - Pr-S (Box 51)
    - V-W (Box 52)
    - Book Reviews (Box 52)
    - Works by Others (Box 53)
  - Subseries IV.4. Research Files
    - A-F (Box 54)
    - I-P (Box 55)
    - R-V (Box 56)
  - Subseries IV.5. Teaching
    - Undergraduate Courses (Box 57)
    - Graduate Dissertations (Box 58)
    - Graduate Orals (Box 59)
    - Departmental Affairs (Box 59)